L. Quincy Mumford Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
L. Quincy Mumford Papers 1939-1982 (bulk 1954-1974)
MSS61916
Mumford, L. Quincy (Lawrence Quincy), 1903-1982
750 items
3 containers
1.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Librarian of Congress. Correspondence, writings, bibliographical material, committee reports, congressional bills, reports, newspaper clippings, and photographs relating to Mumford’s career as a librarian.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Mumford, L. Quincy (Lawrence Quincy), 1903-1982.
Organizations
Library of Congress--Officials and employees.; Library of Congress.
Places
Libraries--Washington (D.C.)
Titles
Lawrence Quincy Mumford papers
Occupations
Librarians of Congress.
Provenance
The papers of L. Quincy Mumford, Librarian of Congress, were given to the Library of Congress by his widow, Betsy P. Mumford, in 1985. A previous acquisition, consisting of nine certificates of greeting transferred from the Central Services Division of the Library, was withdrawn from the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection and combined with Mrs. Mumford’s gift.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of L. Quincy Mumford are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1903, Dec. 11 Born, Ayden, N. C.
1925 Graduated, Duke University, Durham, N. C.
1926 1928 Head of circulation and acting chief of reference, Duke University Library, Durham, N.C.
1928 M.A. in English, Duke University, Durham, N.C.
1929 B.S. in library service, Columbia University, New York, N. Y.
1929 1945 Held various administrative positions, New York Public Library, New York, N.Y. (on leave of absence, 1940-1942)
1930 Married Permelia Catherine Stevens (died 1961)
1940 1942 Special appointment as director, Processing Department, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
1945 Named assistant director, Cleveland Public Library, Cleveland, Ohio
1947 1948 President, Ohio Library Association
1950 1954 Director, Cleveland Public Library, Cleveland, Ohio
1954 1955 President, American Library Association
1954 Appointed Librarian of Congress
1969 Married Betsy Perrin Fox
1974 Retired from the Library of Congress
1982, Aug. 15 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Lawrence Quincy Mumford (1903-1982) cover the years 1939-1982, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1954 to 1974, including correspondence, writings, bibliographical material, invitations, schedules, programs, committee reports, congressional bills, reports, newspaper clippings, and photographs.
Mumford’s correspondence chiefly reflects the personal aspects of his career, beginning with his special appointment as director of the Processing Department at the Library of Congress while on leave of absence from New York Public Library, 1940-1942. His nomination as Librarian of Congress by President Dwight D. Eisenhower in 1954 is documented by letters of support and congratulations from Library colleagues. His correspondence as librarian consists primarily of letters of thanks and recommendation and reflects the social and cultural duties of his office.
The writings consist of articles by Mumford and publications by others on topics of interest to him.
A miscellany file includes appointment schedules, invitations, and programs; biographical file; committee reports; conference file; congressional bills, reports, and hearings; newspaper clippings; and photographs.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is organized by type of material.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1940-1945, 1953-1980, undated, (9 folders) (Box 1)
- Writings (Box 2)
  - By Mumford, 1954-1970 (Box 2)
  - By others, 1939-1982, (4 folders) (Box 2)
- Miscellany (Box 3)
  - Appointment schedules, invitations, programs, 1954-1964, 1973-1979, (12 folders) (Box 3)
  - Biographical material, 1954-1981 (Box 3)
  - Committee reports, 1962, 1972, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Conference file, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Congressional bills, hearings, and reports, 1949-1967 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1945-1974, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)